hey what's up everybody my name is jeff
and i make programming tutorials over at
fireship io
and something people often ask me is how
do i make my videos
so today i'll show you everything i've
learned over the last few years about
building high quality programming
content for youtube
i started my channel in 2017 without any
video production skills
and it's grown to over 400 000
subscribers and a full-time income
over the next few minutes you'll learn
about the tools i use my workflow
and just generally how i approach
content creation the best time to start
a youtube channel was 15 years ago the
second best time
is right now video content ages quickly
and that means there's almost endless
possibilities for creators to build a
business on this platform but if you're
sitting there with zero subscribers
it might seem like an impossible goal
how do you start with absolutely no
social following and build a big youtube
channel
it's actually really simple just focus
on creating high quality content
consistently
and try to make each new video better
than the last what happens is you start
building this positive feedback loop and
it grows bigger and bigger over time
use other creators as inspiration but
really try to embrace your own unique
voice and style
when you find that voice things become
easy you don't need to be anything
special i'm just an introverted nobody
what you do need to have is passion for
what you do and on a deeper level than
just money or internet fame
if you don't have that passion right now
you'll never stick it out and you'll
never be happy doing it
but if you do have that passion then
you'll first need some hardware
you don't need anything expensive or
fancy it's 99
skill and hard work and maybe one
percent the equipment you own
my actual hardware has barely changed
from the day i started you're looking at
my actual setup here
all you need is a microphone a computer
and some software
you don't need to invest thousands of
dollars into building your own studio
just keep it simple
when it comes to hardware what is
important is having a decent microphone
and that's because low quality audio is
the quickest way to drop a viewer on
youtube
if you have bad audio on a programming
tutorial your video is going to be
unwatchable even if the visuals are
awesome all you really need is a decent
usb condenser mic which you can get for
under 100 bucks
the only other hardware you need is a
computer i prefer windows however macs
are a good choice as well
it'll help to have some decent specs on
your machine because much of the
software we use for video editing is
resource intensive
you'll want at least 16 gigs of ram the
best cpu you can afford
and an nvidia graphics card is useful as
well it can take a really long time to
render out video files in hd or 4k
and a more powerful computer will just
help you get things done faster
it's also worth noting that i don't show
my face in my videos so if you do want
to show your face you'll have to talk to
a face youtuber to figure out how that
works you probably need a webcam and a
green screen and that kind of stuff
now let's switch gears by talking about
the software i use which is far more
important the single most important tool
i use is adobe premiere
i have a subscription to adobe creative
cloud which is 52
a month and it's well worth the expense
if you produce a lot of videos
i'll show you my workflow in premiere in
just a minute but essentially it's just
a tool that gives you a timeline where
you can combine multiple audio and video
clips together into a single package
now many of my videos contain shorter
more advanced animations
and for that i use a tool called adobe
after effects it has more advanced
animation tools and it's good for short
clips that you can then render out
and bring into adobe premiere to combine
into your final video
now when it comes to static graphics and
other images that you might see in my
videos
i tend to use figma most often figma is
free for individuals and you can access
all of your assets on the web as well
depending on the type of graphics you
produce figma might be a little too
limited for you
but if you have adobe creative cloud you
also have access to photoshop and
illustrator
which are also good options for static
graphics all this software takes time to
learn
but luckily there are a lot of pre-built
templates out there for you to make
professional videos with minimal effort
the primary hub that i use to access
graphics and pre-built templates
is video hive it contains a ton of after
effects and premiere templates that you
can use to quickly add titles
transitions and logo intros and all
kinds of stuff to your videos
for example you can find a fancy logo
intro swap out your logo
and now you have a professional logo
sting for 20 bucks and maybe an hour of
work
aside from templates you'll also likely
want stock photography
and other graphic assets to use in your
videos there are plenty of places where
you can buy stock photography but the
place i look first
is either unsplash or pexels these sites
have a huge collection of free images
and they're entirely free
another element that i use in many of my
videos are animated gifs
and i source those from giphy not all
gifs can be freely used in your videos
though so make sure to respect the
copyright of the artist that created it
and lastly i use a lot of icons and
emojis in my videos and i primarily get
those graphics from flatikon.com
i pay 10 bucks a month for this service
however they do have a free tier as well
okay so now that you know the tools i
use and where i get things i want to
talk about how i approach
content creation for programmers my
strategy has always been to distill
content down
to the most efficient possible form the
majority of programming tutorials out
there are very long anywhere from 20
minutes to 5 hours
content like that is generally great for
beginners but as an experienced
developer i have a very hard time
sitting through content that long
in most of my videos i make the
assumption that the audience is made up
primarily of intermediate level
developers
by making that assumption i can omit the
very basic stuff and get right into the
intermediate to advanced level stuff
that the audience will find
interesting the bottom line there is
know your audience and craft your
content around what you think the
audience wants
as your channel grows you'll learn that
you can't please all the people all the
time
[Music]
really try to learn from the negative
criticisms that you get from people on
youtube
most critics are people that actually
like you and want to watch your channel
grow
and some people out there will just be
mean for the sake of being mean but you
should never let that go to your heart
because a person who spends their
limited time here as an internet troll
is someone you should feel sorry for
more than anything now let's get down to
brass tacks and look at my actual
workflow for producing a video
now because i produce code tutorials the
first thing i do is write some code
i'm not going to get into the details of
that but let's just assume that i have a
full working project here that i want to
teach the audience about
i just wrote this code so i know exactly
how it works and the next thing i do
is open up adobe premiere to a template
that i have that has some of my reusable
assets in it
now a lot of people think that i write a
script for every video because they
sound scripted
but that's actually not the case what i
actually do is focus on the voiceover
first and i do that right here in
premiere by clicking the record icon
in the timeline i record the audio in a
bunch of small chunks
almost sentence by sentence when i have
the phrase i want to use i use the razer
tool
to cut that piece of audio and then put
it together with the rest of the dialog
i often record the entire dialog before
i add any visual assets to the video
as you can see here in the recording for
this very video that's exactly what i'm
doing
after i record all the audio clips i
nest them together
and then go into essential sound and set
them as the dialog
in this panel i automatch the loudness
which will give it a consistent
broadcast volume
and i also like to add a de-esser and
possibly a vocal enhancer to make the
sound of the voice a little more rich
now that that's done we need to fill up
our video with some visuals i'd
recommend spending the most time making
the visuals at the beginning of the
video really good
the first 60 seconds is your best
opportunity to set the tone for the
video and really inspire the viewer to
see it through until the end
the video's watch time or viewer
retention is really important for
getting that video promoted through
youtube's algorithm
try to keep long pauses to a minimum and
give your viewer a consistent feed of
useful information
when i present a graphic on the screen
it typically only stays there for one to
five seconds
at this point the graphics can really
emphasize what you've already said in
the dialog
after the initial intro we need to show
the actual code that we're working on
many tutorials will show the programmer
writing out the code line by line in
real time
this is very slow and also very error
prone it is more realistic
that way but that's not really what
we're going for here here's how i do it
when i have a code snippet that i'm
talking about i first delete it in
reverse order
after that i start my screen recorder
and then i hit ctrl z
or undo to record each snippet being
inserted
into the document one by one i can then
take that screen recording and just lay
it right on top of my audio track
now it is difficult to get the timing
perfectly right here so one useful
technique
is to add a frame hold to your actual
video which is kind of like taking a
screenshot
so you can hold that position while
you're talking about it and if it's not
clear what line of code you're talking
about i'd recommend throwing in an emoji
or some other graphic that explains what
that line of code is doing with text
that way if the user pauses the video
they can look at that line of code and
really understand what it's all about
now once you have all the pieces put
together
ideally take a long break or sleep on it
and come back to the video with a fresh
set of eyes tomorrow
then watch it critically as if you were
the end viewer do anything you can
to polish or improve the quality of the
video before rendering it to
upload to youtube once you're happy with
the quality your next important
consideration
is the title and the thumbnail a catchy
title and thumbnail will improve the
click-through rate and get your video
seen by more people on youtube
that's a whole nother topic that i might
break down in a future video if you want
to see it let me know in the comments
i'm going to go ahead and wrap things up
there i hope this video gave you some
insight into how i produce my own videos
but keep in mind that there's no one
right way to do things and you will
definitely find your own path when you
start putting in the work
make sure to subscribe to my personal
channel here on youtube for more videos
like this in the future
thanks for watching and i will see you
in the next one